<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</title>
    <link>http://balaramadurai.net/tags/triz/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) Dr. Bala Ramadurai; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://balaramadurai.net/tags/triz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gazing into the Crystal Ball using TRIZ technology trends</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2012/10/13/gazing-into-the-crystal-ball-using-triz-technology-trends/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2012 18:40:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2012/10/13/gazing-into-the-crystal-ball-using-triz-technology-trends/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/art,ball,black,and,white,crystal,light,planet-406f5e2182df35968727c56552e97dc6_h.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;http://cdnimg.visualizeus.com/thumbs/40/6f/art,ball,black,and,white,crystal,light,planet-406f5e2182df35968727c56552e97dc6_h.jpg &amp;quot;courtesy link - http://cdnimg.visualizeus.com/thumbs/40/6f/art,ball,black,and,white,crystal,light,planet-406f5e2182df35968727c56552e97dc6_h.jpg&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 innovation facilitators - Murali Loganathan, Prakasan Kappoth and Bala Ramadurai discuss about the laws of technology evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://trizindia.org/profiles/blogs/8-triz-evolution-trends-applied-to-mobile&#34;&gt;http://trizindia.org/profiles/blogs/8-triz-evolution-trends-applied-to-mobile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the link to the original blog post of the podcast. Also check out this link to the Corning Gorilla Glass story - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/09/ff-corning-gorilla-glass/3/&#34;&gt;http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/09/ff-corning-gorilla-glass/3/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://archive.org/download/TrizInnovationIndiaPodcast-TrendsOfTechnologyEvolution/TRIZIndiapodcast-Trends.mp3&#34;&gt;Listen to the podcast here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_Image Courtesy: &lt;a href=&#34;http://cdnimg.visualizeus.com/thumbs/40/6f/art,ball,black,and,white,crystal,light,planet-406f5e2182df35968727c56552e97dc6_h.jpg&#34;&gt;http://cdnimg.visualizeus.com/thumbs/40/6f/art,ball,black,and,white,crystal,light,planet-406f5e2182df35968727c56552e97dc6_h.jpg&lt;/a&gt;_&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom Designed Workshop</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/03/custom-designed-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 10:53:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/03/custom-designed-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image8.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image8.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image8&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do budding industrial designers, a professor in industrial design, couple of material scientists and an entrepreneur have in common? A thirst for novelty and the desire to help people. The venue was perfect with movable chairs, a whiteboard, projector, an audio system, just in case, we lost our ability to shout. Ranjan had arranged for flipcharts, markers and motivators. Motivators are little chocolate blocks, which go a long way in crafting excellent design from anyone. Shankar(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/shankarmv&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/shankarmv&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;), the lead facilitator, started off with a brief introduction on what innovation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bringing insightful ideas into a market”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tweet like mantra is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 stages of _!nnovation flow _-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape &amp;amp; Align&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move
Focus is the step where the entire attention is on &amp;ldquo;where the heck is the problem?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Escape &amp;amp; Align is about &amp;ldquo;What all can solve this problem?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Are my ideas science fiction or are they aligned to my organization/customers?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move is about &amp;ldquo;How do take it from here into the future?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bala(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/balaramadurai&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/nikimonikado&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/nikimonikado&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;) laid out the plan for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem selection &amp;amp; team formation Focus: 9 questions, Logo, Ideal Final Result, 5-Whys, function mapping Escape&amp;amp;Align: SCAMPER&amp;amp;IFR, Visual Business Model Move: Wasn’t covered as part of this workshop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sridhar(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/sridhardp&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/ThatvaTweet&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;) gave an overview of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thatva.com/&#34;&gt;Thatva&lt;/a&gt; which was a big part of the workshop as it gave a workspace for the teams to work out their ideas. The Thatva tool guided the teams to formalize their plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 ladies were appointed team captains and was asked to form their own teams of 4 members. There was intense chaos, but resulted in naturally formed cohesive teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task 1: Pick a socially relevant problem to solve and name your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task 2: Draw a good logo for your team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All logos are given below. Their logo pretty much depicts their problem statement as well. A fun way to focus, we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;logos&#34;&gt;Logos&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that made us facilitators worry about the sanity of the team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/scavenger.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/scavenger.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Scavenger&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/scavenger2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/scavenger2.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Scavenger- team in action&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whacky team, and a creative one!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that made us cry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/caresquare.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/caresquare.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Caresquare&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/caresquare2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/caresquare2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Caresquare - team in action&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Democracy at work, this team, everyone was listened to, well, almost everyone ;-)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that went thru more revisions than the colours on their logo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/helios.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/helios.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Helios&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you lack content, use colour :-)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that was corny&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/mealmonitors.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/mealmonitors.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;MealMonitors&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tagline says it all&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that had one guy do all the work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Leaf and newleafers leafing new leafs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-v0k128rvZLs/TtT7adY_-2I/AAAAAAAAAms/X-z1RKkKqZM/s720/DSC00678.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;H3O - the logo that required a long winded explanation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ideal-final-result-and-incubation&#34;&gt;Ideal Final Result and Incubation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the slogans, logo, initial discussions were over, ’twas analysis time. Top 3 benefits, 3 deficiencies, 3 dollar costs of the current situation was analyzed. 5-whys applied to find root cause of the problems, rather than stop at the first instance of trouble. The budding designers really liked the simplicity of the tool and the impact that the tool left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The smiling Prof. Chakrabarti&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incubation Time: The teams had to draw in pictures their problem with a funny restriction - No Words! SIPOC or supplier, inputs, process, output and customer was used as a template for the function mapping. This was given as overnight assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1 drew to a closure. We had promised a day of hardwork and so it was, big grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2 started with Sridhar guiding the teams to enter their output into Thatva and some basics on business plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was fun day - Started with silent brainstorming - Write down all ideas that pop in to your head to solve the problem as illustrated in the various tools of Focus. As much as 30 ideas emerged per team. Guided ideation - SCAMPER or substitute, combine, adapt, minimize/maximize, put to other use, eliminate, reverse was put to use. The teams found SCAMP quite good and added more ideas to their kitty. For Adapt, role play was used. Questions like &amp;ldquo;What would Superman do [if he were to solve your problem]?&amp;rdquo; not only sent out giggles around the room, but some unheard of ideas. Eliminate and Reverse were the toughest ones for the participants. Some really good ideas emerged for teams who persisted with their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does a team with a lot of ideas do? Giggle, snicker, doze and merge ideas into a concept. A concept chart was drawn out of all or most ideas during the session. This was presented amidst some power outages as seen in the pictures. Nothing stops enthusiastic students from presenting their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ended a great 2 half days for all of us. The students didn’t realize that they had taught the facilitators a great deal more than what was expected. A grand gala lunch followed in Nesara restaurant in IISc, Bangalore. We were richer by a few more facebook friends! Of course, a big thanks to Prof. Amaresh Chakrabarti and all his enthusiastic students who gave us the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other pictures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;622&amp;rdquo; caption=&amp;ldquo;The entire gang of participants, facilitators and the Professor&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;img/DSC00681.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The entire gang of participants, facilitators and the Professor&#34; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;576&amp;rdquo; caption=&amp;ldquo;Post workshop - Lunch at Nesara, IISc&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;img/DSC00683.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Post workshop - Lunch at Nesara, IISc&#34; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Steps to Alleviate All Your Worries</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/04/3-steps-to-alleviate-all-your-worries/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 12:13:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/04/3-steps-to-alleviate-all-your-worries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I hit upon a key insight when I replied to a mail after a recent community session. The session was on how to attain high productivity in life and work. This is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rahulbijlani.com/essays/you-are-not-running-out-of-time-essay/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; I got from Venkat about an article on how one never runs short of time, if one has the purpose figured out. In there was an anecdote from &amp;ldquo;Zen and the art of motorcycle maintenance&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Eventually, I came across a thought from ‘Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance’. In the story, Pirsig, a young man, goes mountain-climbing with some elderly monks. He struggles throughout, and eventually gives up, while the monks easily continue to the peak. What is apparent is that Pirsig, focussed as he is on the peak, is overwhelmed by the climb, and continues to lose his desire and strength with every step. The monks, on the other hand, used the peak only as a guide to mark the direction of their climb; they were more focused on the journey and its enjoyment, and made it to the top with ease.&amp;rdquo; This is from the essay given in the link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the message is about &amp;ldquo;being in the moment&amp;rdquo; than lost in worry. Now, I thought about how else could Pirsig have made his journey better. Bing! Then it dawned on me that all Pirsig had to was to visualize himself standing on the peak. Or better still, carried a picture of the peak (Printed off the internet using Google Street View or from the myriads of pictures that enthusiastic tourists upload :)). The key is to move the concern from the prefrontal cortex (PFC) to the visual cortex of the brain. So how does that help? PFC is the last evolved portion of the human brain and hence is very low in energy efficiency. Any thoughts in this portion of the brain can be a drag on the brain&amp;rsquo;s resources. Visual cortex, however, has it all figured out and can handle any number of images. Once, the thought/concern moves to the visual cortex, PFC is free to enjoy the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image003.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image003.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Prefrontal Cortex and the Brain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What to do when a concern/worry hits you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. write it down on a piece of paper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Close your eyes and imagine yourself having completely solved the problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. open your eyes and focus on what to do to alleviate the worry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In TRIZ toolkit, ideal final result (IFR) is about imagining a future where there is only good stuff or benefits. Now, one can add a visual to this IFR and get down to solving problems which are preventing one from getting to an IFR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>