<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</title>
    <link>http://balaramadurai.net/categories/writing/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) Dr. Bala Ramadurai; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://balaramadurai.net/categories/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>She was not his boss</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/10/she-was-not-his-boss/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2011 11:46:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/10/she-was-not-his-boss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;She certainly was not his boss, neither did they have any sort of agreement written between themselves. In fact, this was the first time, they had met. Till that moment, he was a maverick, picking up whatever he wanted from the retail store. It was evident to all who cared to look at his activities, that he was not interested in buying any of the stuff that he picked up. These actions were becoming routine - pick up a few items and leave them on the floor for someone to put back on shelf. The store employees were fine with this. How come she had a problem? How come she wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing any of this even though there was so many opportunities to do so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Heeeeyyyyy&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; was the yell that came from her, when he approached the aisle one more time with the sole intention of throwing the plastic sport glasses onto the floor. He froze. He turned around to see her with hands on her hips and an angry glare. No words exchanged so far. The communication was absolutely 100% non-verbal. He moved onto the clothes section now, very well knowing that a pair of eyes was scrutinizing his behaviour. The ethnic section had tons of loose clothing and things were in a mess already. Who&amp;rsquo;s going to notice if a few more were added to the pile. He could see a hand in front of him now. What sort of a managerial gimmick is this, that too from a total stranger? This time she was just plain playful. Phew! He heaved a sigh of relief, not all work, there&amp;rsquo;s some play in her. She played peek-a-boo, hid herself in the clothes and out she came. He was amused, one could tell from the hysterical giggles from both parties. Will this play go on or is there some seriousness? He lost interest in the game, moved quickly, casting a few of his magnetic smiles to the oncoming people. He was a social magnet and also knew that speed was of the essence. He lost her, but somehow missed her as well. He turned around to see if he could see the green clothed non-boss boss. Nope.. all clear. He went back to the same aisle. Nope, she had moved on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed all this happen, it made me wonder - she was all of 2.5 years, he was nearing 1.5 in another week, how did she know that this boy responds to &amp;ldquo;heeeyyy..&amp;rdquo; or rolling of eyes or squeals? All of this were beyond words, no words exchanged. How does one know what one responds to ? When does one switch strategy? Kids seem to know it. Leadership or parenting lessons, anyone?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What goes around comes around</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/26/what-goes-around-comes-around/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2011 10:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/26/what-goes-around-comes-around/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“Baaammmm&amp;hellip;” was the huge noise that was heard when our car hit a black SX-4 while zigzagging in Chennai traffic. This happened a few years ago near a Chennai suburb called Padi. I was acting consultant to a large car component manufacturer. Alongside with me was a professor of mine who was also consulting with this company. He had invited me to give a talk to a bunch of trainee engineers and senior management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An hour ago&amp;hellip;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prof O and me had a long journey from Adyar to Padi, residential southern end of Chennai to the north-western industrial end of Chennai. We were chitchatting on the intricacies of my world and his world. All along, a black sedan was “driving like crazy” in the corner of my eye. Our driver, Raju, had actually revved up a few times. Since, prof O and I were so lost in our conversation, neither of us paid attention, since I had a job at hand of convincing the management about the limitations of their instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just before a traffic signal, the black sedan suddenly cut across and Raju lost it. Prof O and I were still deep in scientific conversation. Raju&amp;rsquo;s feet slammed the brakes and he moaned and looked at his rear view mirror to see if we had noticed. This is
when I noticed that there was something amiss and I remarked it to the professor. Before, he could say anything, the black sedan
zipped past us and Raju revved up and in 3 seconds, he not only caught up with the sedan, also cut across. Raju had misjudged the maneuver and “Baaaammm”, ended damaging the black sedan. Both vehicles stopped. The driver of the black sedan stepped out, a young gentleman about 25-30 years old, medium build and dressed in a safari suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Enna saaar?” quizzed the sedan driver with his thumbs up, a typical &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s up&amp;rdquo; of Chennai. I thought that was a typical Tamil gesture of asking a question. He was seething with anger and looked at us. Prof O shrugged his shoulders and said in English “We are consultants, we have nothing to do with this car”. The attention now shifted to Raju, who was aghast at what he had done. What followed was shocking&amp;hellip; Raju unfastened his seatbelt and stepped out of the car and was about to examine the damage. The sedan driver slapped Raju on his face with his right hand and uttered words that I can&amp;rsquo;t write here. Raju didn&amp;rsquo;t say a word. We expected retaliation or war of words from Raju. Nothing! He stood his ground and quietly told the sedan driver that he was
sorry for the behaviour and promised to pay up for the damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20 minutes of negotiation with the driver at a distance from us and Raju got back into the car. No microscopy or materials science talk after that, it was just the filtered traffic noise and the hum of the A/C. We reached our destination and got out of the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My session went well and the management seemed happy with my analysis of their instrument and we were ready to return. We were waiting for Raju and his car. Raju came by walk and was his usual smiling self. Prof O asked him about the morning&amp;rsquo;s events. Raju admitted that the sedan&amp;rsquo;s movements pulled him into an unnecessary dual, which resulted in the damage of the sedan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Everything&amp;rsquo;s even now”, said Raju.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean?” asked a surprised Prof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Narasimha is a courier person to our company and he has been late in bringing his shipments on 3-4 occasions and owes us money. So we settled with him and we are no longer continuing business with him”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Who is Narasimha?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The driver who hit us, saar. He is Narasimha and I am in-charge of handling couriers in this company from now on” smiled Raju&amp;hellip; “He shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have slapped me, saar. That is why he is paying for this”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Steps to Alleviate All Your Worries</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/04/3-steps-to-alleviate-all-your-worries/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 12:13:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/04/3-steps-to-alleviate-all-your-worries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I hit upon a key insight when I replied to a mail after a recent community session. The session was on how to attain high productivity in life and work. This is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rahulbijlani.com/essays/you-are-not-running-out-of-time-essay/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; I got from Venkat about an article on how one never runs short of time, if one has the purpose figured out. In there was an anecdote from &amp;ldquo;Zen and the art of motorcycle maintenance&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Eventually, I came across a thought from ‘Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance’. In the story, Pirsig, a young man, goes mountain-climbing with some elderly monks. He struggles throughout, and eventually gives up, while the monks easily continue to the peak. What is apparent is that Pirsig, focussed as he is on the peak, is overwhelmed by the climb, and continues to lose his desire and strength with every step. The monks, on the other hand, used the peak only as a guide to mark the direction of their climb; they were more focused on the journey and its enjoyment, and made it to the top with ease.&amp;rdquo; This is from the essay given in the link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the message is about &amp;ldquo;being in the moment&amp;rdquo; than lost in worry. Now, I thought about how else could Pirsig have made his journey better. Bing! Then it dawned on me that all Pirsig had to was to visualize himself standing on the peak. Or better still, carried a picture of the peak (Printed off the internet using Google Street View or from the myriads of pictures that enthusiastic tourists upload :)). The key is to move the concern from the prefrontal cortex (PFC) to the visual cortex of the brain. So how does that help? PFC is the last evolved portion of the human brain and hence is very low in energy efficiency. Any thoughts in this portion of the brain can be a drag on the brain&amp;rsquo;s resources. Visual cortex, however, has it all figured out and can handle any number of images. Once, the thought/concern moves to the visual cortex, PFC is free to enjoy the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image003.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image003.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Prefrontal Cortex and the Brain&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What to do when a concern/worry hits you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. write it down on a piece of paper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Close your eyes and imagine yourself having completely solved the problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. open your eyes and focus on what to do to alleviate the worry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In TRIZ toolkit, ideal final result (IFR) is about imagining a future where there is only good stuff or benefits. Now, one can add a visual to this IFR and get down to solving problems which are preventing one from getting to an IFR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>