<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</title>
    <link>http://balaramadurai.net/categories/teaching/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) Dr. Bala Ramadurai; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://balaramadurai.net/categories/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Karmic Design Thinking - Part 3 - Defining Structure</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/22/karmic-design-thinking-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 17:38:21 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/22/karmic-design-thinking-3/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/karmic-design-thinking.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;karmic design thinking&#34; class=&#34;img-responsive&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To refresh on stuff - &lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/08/karmic-design-thinking-1/&#34;&gt;Rethinking Design Thinking&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/15/karmic-design-thinking-2/&#34;&gt;What is Karmic Design Thinking&lt;/a&gt; were things that I talked about earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broad design of this form of design thinking consists of these four stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I. People Orientation&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;System Orientation&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
This is the stage in which we acknowledge the deficiencies in the system and try and find out about what is it that people are going through. Or if it
is a device or a service, our job is to figure out what is it that this system is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the people part.
Some questions to be figured out in this stage are:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Who are you trying to help?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Note - Talk to real people. Figure out who these people are. Their age, gender, geography and just for fun, a fictional name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you could say, Poornima, 35, is a mom in New Delhi. She has to drive to work and that is the activity we would like to track. We would
first see what it is that Poornima suffers from in her ordinary activity like driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I would like to add that just like people have a voice and they can tell us what they want. We should be helping them for sure, however,
machines or systems also have a certain &amp;ldquo;voice&amp;rdquo; that needs to be studied as well. I call it the system based approach. One perspective is that people
define how their environment is going to be, but the other perspective is that people adapt according to their environment. So, it is equally
important to consider the system perspective as well. In fact, if you don&amp;rsquo;t get reasonable insights from the people, walk up to the devices that they
use and (with their permission) unearth some insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, one could take a product like a coconut scraper, you know the device that is used to scrape out coconut flesh (?) from the shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are you trying to improve?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is the system based question. The system is defined as the aspects of the environment that you are allowed to change. If something cannot be changed by you, then we can term it as the outside or in a system operator parlance, it is usually called the supersystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is their suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Note - Examine a particular product or service that can you can lay your hands on. You should be able to observe and talk to these real people while they are using the product or service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are they sad about?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What makes them furious?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What makes them feel helpless?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What makes them feel jealous about someone else who is better off than them?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Which part of the system needs to be fixed?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will use some tools of thinking to figure these out.&lt;br /&gt;
Another note - when I mention &amp;lsquo;tools&amp;rsquo;, they usually imply tools of thinking, thought experiments. One could use any method to find this out. I will
describe some of the popular methods used for this step, however, you are free to choose which method you want to use in this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;II. Problem Definition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Why are they suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What are the reasons for this state that people or systems are in?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We will use tools of &lt;a href=&#34;http://trizindia.org&#34;&gt;TRIZ&lt;/a&gt; to help out here. We need to look at the root cause of suffering. Again, here you can choose a method that suits your taste
and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How did the suffering come into being?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What does a world without the suffering look like?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What is the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Nirvana&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Nibbana&lt;/strong&gt;[in Pali, an old Indian language] &lt;em&gt;for such a state of continued suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;III. Solution Generation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How can the suffering be cured?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We will tap into the vast resources of human ingenuity for solutions, aka TRIZ. We can use our inner potential for this as well. Deep, immersive meditation, blissful sleep are as powerful for idea generation as ideas inspired by falling spiders or apples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IV. Concept Consolidation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What is the exact path to be taken to end the suffering?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It is not enough if we have great ideas for the betterment of people or systems around us, we need to have it all consolidated into one neat package
that we can deliver on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you will gain out of following such a path of design thinking is given in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;liberation&#34;&gt;Liberation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire flow of the design thinking process is summed up in the Figure below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/Karmic.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;flowchart of karmic design thinking&#34; class=&#34;img-responsive&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This is the flowchart of Karmic Design Thinking, retrospectively, heavily inspired by Lord Buddha&amp;rsquo;s Four Noble Truths&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iterations of the process can lead to rock solid design that liberates your customer from suffering. This is the ultimate goal of all the
products/services/businesses to help the users or customers attain Nirvana. Using our inspiration from Lord Buddha, we need our products to attain a
state of Nirvana as well. They leave their goodness behind but they themselves may not be there in their product form. For example, the need to tell
time has always been around. We as humanity have used the sun and stars for telling us the time. The several generations of products in this regard
have tried to deliver this functionality of telling time. Now, this function was on our wrists (wrist watch) and then unceremoniously to the mobile
phone. Now, the &amp;ldquo;wearable&amp;rdquo; gadgets are back. But, they are this close to attaining Nirvana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A feature here, a form change here, a bug removed, a color added here. In the linear growth stage
of the S-curve (logistic growth phase), the products gain the above said things - form, features, colors. They also lose certain things - bugs, number
of components, number of steps/clicks. The cost doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to change a whole lot during this phase. By cost, we imply the resources that the product
or service consumes in order to be a product. Then towards the end of life, the product or service starts reducing the intake of resources and also
loses the benefits or features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is best illustrated using the equation from the TRIZ world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/IFR-eqn.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Ideal Final Result Equation&#34; class=&#34;img-responsive&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the product or service is ready to enter the next generation or if it is mature enough is ready to be absorbed by another product or service in
totality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This end of all the S-curves is what I term Liberation or what Lord Buddha called Nirvana or Nibbana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be up to date with my blog posts, you can subscribe to my blog or join in the discussion below.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Karmic Design Thinking - Part 2 - What is it?</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/15/karmic-design-thinking-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 14:46:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/15/karmic-design-thinking-2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Aahaa&amp;rdquo; moment  that  &lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/08/karmic-design-thinking-1/&#34;&gt;design thinking&lt;/a&gt; is probably much older than only a few decades. That moment came to me when I traveled to an ancient set of Buddhist caves in India. These caves are located in central India and are at least 2000 years old. Ajanta caves, as they are called, were lost to humanity for about 1000 odd years before a British soldier rediscovered the caves in his hunting expedition. If you are planning on visiting Mumbai or Pune, I would highly recommend visiting these caves and spend a few days admiring these beautiful caves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/Buddha.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Mahaparinirvana&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mahaparinirvana or the attaining of Nirvana: This sculpture is my personal favorite (Cave #26). The top line of angels look happy and the bottom set of people look sad. The angels are happy since they will have Lord Buddha in their midst and the bottom set of earth people are sad because the Buddha is leaving them&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my bid to prepare for this trip to the ancient caves, I read up about the story of the British soldier, John Smith, and many more from the usual
sources like Wikipedia. The story goes something like this. The soldier, to leave his mark behind, even climbed up a pile of wood piled up near a pillar, and signed his name (Please
check out cave #10 and the right hand side pillar in the front at the height of about 7-8 feet to see the engraved name of the soldier. Vandalism
becomes part of history :) )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lord-buddha-s-four-noble-truths&#34;&gt;Lord Buddha&amp;rsquo;s Four Noble Truths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reading is usually part of my preparation for travel to any place. I stumbled upon an article on Gautham Buddha&amp;rsquo;s four noble truths. The article on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Noble_Truths&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; mentioned that Buddha first postulated his noble truths to his five disciples in Sarnath in a deer park. His insights came from his 49 day meditation marathon in Bodh Gaya, India under a tree. Now, these four noble truths were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dukkha&lt;/em&gt; - What is the suffering that people are going through - due to disease, old age, rebirth, jealousy and what not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Samudaya&lt;/em&gt; - Why are they suffering? What are the reasons for their suffering?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Niroda&lt;/em&gt; - How does one resolve the reasons for suffering?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Magga&lt;/em&gt; - What is the path that will put an end to that suffering?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I jumped with joy when I came to know of this explanation. In my mind, I did an exact one to one correlation of my &amp;ldquo;design thinking&amp;rdquo; design
and the four noble truths that Buddha had put forward two and a half thousand years ago. My happiness knew no bounds and I felt the energy to explain everything around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt deflated and elated at the same time. Only a TRIZ trained guy can write a statement like that and feel elated that one could write a statement like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deflated because of the feeling that someone before me had invented this &amp;ldquo;design&amp;rdquo;. And that I had missed being the first guy to invent by about 2,500
years. Elated because this &amp;ldquo;design&amp;rdquo; has really stood the test of time. There are scores of people who have followed this paradigm and are current
followers. You know, it is a religion now and not just a random design by some random blogger/teacher sitting in front of a laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;purpose-of-design-thinking&#34;&gt;Purpose of Design Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question that popped into my mind was - Ok, for once, let us assume what Lord Buddha talked about IS design thinking. But, what is the purpose
of design thinking? What does one do with that? How could one use that in real work life or student life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I turned to my personal spiritual Guru Shakya Muni (&lt;em&gt;aka&lt;/em&gt; Buddha) for the answer. &amp;ldquo;To escape the birth-rebirth cycles&amp;rdquo; was the answer that he gave in 500 BC. Hmmm.. Tough one to decipher even in English. I thought about it for a long time and I meditated on that one as to what that may mean for me and my course design (Yes, yes, I do meditate every day for 15 minutes religiously).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me one fine Wednesday morning (The day is not important since I made that one up) when my old trusted, but rusted phone asked if I minded if it updated me. I said yes and my rusted phone yowled at me saying that I had insufficient storage. In a bit of rage, I must have said something to the effect that it was my earlier birth&amp;rsquo;s Karma that I had landed up with such a phone. Oh, please don&amp;rsquo;t tell my phone that I said that. I really like my rusted phone. I can still put it in my pocket and there is no need to carry it in my hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, that was my trigger - multi-generations of software/hardware. That is what we are trying to escape. That is what Buddha was trying to tell us and it took me 2500 years of births and rebirths to understand this. No, not the android upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every product or service is designed and redesigned to adapt to all possible needs and wants from the customer. Every product goes through a
transformation from birth to death, usually referred to as an S-curve. The hockey stick curve which was independently discovered in four different
fields. This is one S-curve for one product/service. This transforms as the product ages and finally when the product is phased out, the function is
transferred to some other product/service before it finally, er&amp;hellip;, croaks. The product starts out as a new kid in the block with a few geeks using
it. Imagine that holding plastic boxes next to ear was a kid&amp;rsquo;s game about 25-30 years ago. Adults used to snigger and let the kids play with their
&amp;ldquo;imagination&amp;rdquo; and comment to their colleagues &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know where they get their stupid ideas from. Holding plastic boxes next to their ears and then
staring at the same plastic boxes for the next hour or so. Kids these days need better games.&amp;rdquo; The kids of yesteryears had their last laugh when the
same &amp;ldquo;adults&amp;rdquo;, now seniors are hooked on to their Whatsapp screens, playing the same stupid plastic box game years later. Talk about second childhood,
eh, Shakespeare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that new product starts getting accepted by a few more geeks and they spread the word. This phenomenon is described by Malcolm Gladwell in his
book, Tipping Point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, the product starts gathering features and is on a low maintenance mode. Lots of new players mushroom offering their &amp;ldquo;me-too&amp;rdquo; product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once, the product goes past the mid way mark, the market sees consolidation and a few major players keep the lion&amp;rsquo;s share while the rest claw their way into unheard of markets. This is the honeymoon phase for the major players, since without much effort, the cash registers are ringing. Suddenly at some point of time, looks like the feature well has dried up and people have started talking about how the looks are far more important than the function. We have entered the design era of the S-curve. Aesthetics are very important and now, ease of use becomes prime. The product starts becoming simpler, more intelligent and the masses have started using it big time. This is an exciting phase as the price starts dropping with simplicity becoming paramount. Once, in this phase, one starts to see other geeky products hit the market. The next S-curve is priming up for limelight, but it is too early. There is still some life left in the previous S-curve. The next one starts borrowing resources from the previous generation. Abruptly, the current S-curve falls flat and the cash stream has dried up. The companies become sitting ducks for buy-outs. Geeks have already shifted out to trying out the next S-curve, as the trial period has started and the cycle starts all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt that there is too much talk about design and form these days. Was it because I am interested in design that I hear more these days? Or is it reality that people are giving design more thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fud&#34;&gt;FUD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about this even further.&lt;br /&gt;
Now, why is design thinking of interest to the industry or people, out of the blue?&lt;br /&gt;
I imagined a conversation between Lord Buddha (LB) and me (BR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LB: The premise of all this lies in the fact that in the industry, people try to implement ideas so that they can all lead to revenues.&lt;br /&gt;
BR: But, Sir, all that sounds fine, the big question still remains whether all implemented ideas lead to revenue for the company?&lt;br /&gt;
LB: Then, the subsequent argument could be that we only implement revenue generating ideas.&lt;br /&gt;
BR: Sounds simple, but then my interest lies in how these revenue generating ideas are generated?&lt;br /&gt;
LB: It is better to seek these ideas rather than pursue every idea and face dead ends.&lt;br /&gt;
BR: Yes, yes, that would be true in an ideal world, in the world that you are in right now. We still live in a world which is governed by FUD.&lt;br /&gt;
LB: FUD? Is that the name of your ruler?&lt;br /&gt;
BR: Fear, Uncertainty, Doubt. That is what Neo from &amp;ldquo;The Matrix&amp;rdquo; had to let go before jumping off that simulated building, you know when Morpheus asked him to jump.&lt;br /&gt;
LB: Now, why would he do that?&lt;br /&gt;
BR: To attain enlightenment and fly like Superman. There were no Bodhi trees in &amp;ldquo;The Matrix&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;
LB: Oh, that? Have no fear, when I am here. (&lt;em&gt;with right palm raised&lt;/em&gt;) I will quote one from your era for your own reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A problem well stated is a problem half-solved&lt;br /&gt;
Charles Kettering, inventor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BR: I&amp;rsquo;ll write that down. Great, now where do I find these problems?
LB: My disciples never required this level of spoon feeding as you do, Bala.
BR: &amp;ldquo;There is no spoon.&amp;rdquo;
LB: Pardon me.
BR: Never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great, this means I&amp;rsquo;ll have to figure out all this myself. &lt;em&gt;Sheesh!&lt;/em&gt; Consultants were not what they are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s start with the quote. A problem well stated, eh? Hmmm&amp;hellip; That means if we have well defined problems, they are great precursors to these revenue generating ideas. The next big question to attack is - where on earth do I find these problems, so that I can define them well and get well meaning revenue generating ideas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional design thinking seems to suggest people centric approach. Not a bad start. We can observe people as they go about their daily business and
figure out what they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My counter self asked me (you know the jerk inside me. C&amp;rsquo;mon! everyone has one inside, right? Or is it only me? Oh Lord Buddha, I need to see a doc) - Why would that be useful? Observing people and figuring out stuff seems like the wrong path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get many answers from deep within, so I ventured out and researched online. Harvard Business Review seems to have given it some thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many companies large and small are moving from products to services, hardware to software, physical to digital and hence are focussing on user experience&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2015/09/design-thinking-comes-of-age&#34;&gt;Harvard Business Review Article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User experience doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean pretty interfaces and glossy exteriors only, which was the image I carried in my head when I thought about designs and designers. This was up until my designer friends pounced on me and gave my material scientific brain a whacking. Form and function, both are equally important, the whacking had messages like these. As you can see, I have very good friends&amp;hellip; :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;design-thinking&#34;&gt;Design Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, everyone wants to go the design thinking way, but how do they go about it?&lt;br /&gt;
The method suggested by design schools and firms is simple -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find out what customers want by observing them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Draw insights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go right ahead and generate some ideas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take some promising ideas and start prototyping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make mockups, even basic paper and sketch kind of prototyping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give your prototypes to potential customers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, make notes on how these customers use this and how they like it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refine, iterate, repeat, observe, ideate, prototype, test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-redesigned-design-thinking&#34;&gt;The Redesigned Design Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solutions evolve as time progresses and you will get great feedback from your first set of customers. You can fix them and life goes on well. The point where I find troubling is that some set of inspired designers come up with great ideas quickly and hence the process is robust. With the experience of TRIZ and systematic problem solving, I got a sinking feeling about people who don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily feel as inspired as a designer who is knee deep into the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is where I felt the need to combine traditional design thinking approach with the systematic problem solving approach. Systematic problem solving approach kicks in once the problem area is identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/TRIZ-DT.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What if two methodologies talked to each other?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ideal Design Thinking Method = Design Thinking + TRIZ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rebirth-of-design-thinking-karmic-design-thinking&#34;&gt;Rebirth of Design Thinking - Karmic Design Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since, this new thinking methodology is heavily inspired by Lord Buddha&amp;rsquo;s four noble truths, I call this &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; thinking approach as &lt;strong&gt;Karmic
Design Thinking&lt;/strong&gt;, you know, originating out of Karma, the Karma arising out of rebirths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, concluding episode of this series, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/22/karmic-design-thinking-3/&#34;&gt;Karmic Design Thinking - Part 3 - Defining Structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Karmic Design Thinking - Part 1 - Rethinking Design Thinking</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/08/karmic-design-thinking-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 20:34:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/08/karmic-design-thinking-1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/design-1210160_640.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;https://pixabay.com/p-1210160/&#34; title=&#34;https://pixabay.com/p-1210160/&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me stoke your curiosity. I have an important reason to write this series of posts on Karmic Design Thinking. Please promise that you will be patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is ubiquitous and is all around us. A tree is designed to bear the entire weight of the tree on that one single trunk. Ok, you can really say
that, well, design is a conscious process. In my opinion, designs evolve naturally, either by nature or by human intervention. And since we are all
part of nature, it is one and the same. Talk about talking in circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design Thinking is using this kind of thinking in everything around and that could include design. Phew! I am glad that is out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right, right, the reason for the series of posts. I am coming to that, there is no need to yell at a device for that. Ready or not, here&amp;rsquo;s the story of why I felt that this series had to be written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story&#34;&gt;The Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early dry months of 2016, I was asked to teach a course for design thinking for a batch of about 200+ MBA students at Symbiosis Institute of Business Management, Pune, India. On top of that, the course coordinator informed me that this course was a core course which meant that all 219 of them had to starting thinking design thinking. No, I take that back, they had to go through the course and pass the course, or else they would stay back in the lovely hilly campus for another year on my account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I started to redesign the course &amp;ldquo;design thinking&amp;rdquo; as I also thought my material was becoming stale and needed a fresh look. Besides, I love designing courses. Design is everywhere, I just told you a few paragraphs earlier. So &amp;ldquo;stale&amp;rdquo; was an excuse to draw up a completely new design. Since the course was 30 hours long, I split the course into 4 chunks of 7.5 hours each. Remember, I told you I prefer day long teaching rather than an hour here and an hour there. If you are a teacher, who teaches hour by hour, then you can split what I am about to describe into chunks of an hour each as well and it would still make sense for your students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-grand-redesign&#34;&gt;The Grand Redesign&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stages I had chalked out for the course were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People Orientation&lt;/strong&gt; - you have to know what people are going through before you discuss solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem Definition&lt;/strong&gt; - What is the exact cause of whatever it is that the above mentioned people are going through?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution Generation&lt;/strong&gt; - How do you solve the problem effectively, smartly?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concept consolidation&lt;/strong&gt; - Chalk out your next course of action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most design courses around the world, one would add &lt;em&gt;prototyping&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;testing&lt;/em&gt; to these phases. The skill sets required are different for prototyping and there is real money involved in making some of these prototypes. In the 4th stage of concept consolidation, there is some degree of prototyping, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call it that yet. To me, a prototype is something that you can give an intended user to work with and find out how they react to your idea. These four stages appear before prototyping and testing, so that you are at least aware of what is that your intended audience is facing and where is that they need help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was done for the course and I had some associated presentation material, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how the students were going to learn from only me yakking and nothing else concrete to latch on to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;different-strokes-for-different-folks&#34;&gt;Different Strokes for Different Folks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to satisfy three types of learning styles - &lt;em&gt;visual, auditory and kinesthetic&lt;/em&gt; or learning by doing. By way of the course, visual and auditory
styles were going to be satisfied. Audio - my speaking and video - some interesting videos on the internet. What about the kinesthetics? What about the ones who
wanted to learn offline, you know, by not coming to a class, but still want to pick up design thinking? &lt;em&gt;Wink&amp;hellip; Wink&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; Well, to an extent
kinesthetics would benefit from the activities in the course, but offline students left a big void for me. I built a companion course website using
&lt;a href=&#34;http://moodle.org&#34;&gt;moodle&lt;/a&gt;. This worked for the students to some extent, but I felt that they needed a manual, a treatise or a go to repository of information if ever
they got lost designing something. Besides, if I want to jot down every little detail so that I don&amp;rsquo;t have to remember it. Hence, I decided to
document my methods in a series of posts or better still a book. Besides the internet and books usually have a wider and better reach than my physical
presence. Also, I would just point these pesky students to the book/posts and yell at them -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RTFM - &amp;ldquo;Read the friendly manual&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;self-doubt&#34;&gt;Self-Doubt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure of was if this course/book/posts design that I had written down is valid and if it would stand the test of time. I got a bit jittery at
this point with thoughts like what if this model fails after a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could I get the ideas presented here validated?&lt;br /&gt;
Can I get it validated by a known expert and without spending a dime or writing long emails?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I needed a proverbial apple to fall on my head to assure me that all was well with my design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;and&#34;&gt;And&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-info&#34;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;And the apple did fall!&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next exciting episode of Karmic Design Thinking is covered - &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2016/12/15/karmic-design-thinking-2/&#34;&gt;Karmic Design Thinking - Part 2 - What is it?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to know what I have in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are students capable of coming out with blockbuster ideas?</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2012/05/12/are-students-capable-of-coming-out-with-blockbuster-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2012 07:14:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2012/05/12/are-students-capable-of-coming-out-with-blockbuster-ideas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/clapping.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/clapping.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Office Workers Clapping at Office Party&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raging debate in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://venture-lab.org&#34;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; has been whether students (our team picked out undergraduate engineering students in
particular) are capable of generating blockbuster ideas for a thriving business/startup.&lt;br /&gt;
Before giving you both sides of the coin, I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you an anecdote about a large company trying to figure out what makes creative minds
creative. This large company was really curious to find out the real mechanism which made the creative minds work. So, they did surveys and profiling
to figure out (Education, cultural background, family details and so on) what was really happening in their minds. Zilch! They came out with no
concrete patterns or reasons for the creativity in their organization.&lt;br /&gt;
Second round was face to face interviews to see if they were missing out something obvious. After a few interviews, they hit upon the key insight that
they were looking for - creative guys thought that they were creative and the not-so-creative guys thought that they were not creative. Period!
Nothing else! (As a side note, this is what neuro linguistic programming (NLP) is all about :))&lt;br /&gt;
With this background in mind, I go back to the original debate of whether students will come out with ideas. Sure, the students who really believe
that they are creative will crack any problem given to them. The ones who think &amp;quot;Oh no, this is not my cup of tea to rub shoulders with the likes
of Edison&amp;quot;, will remain in the sideranks reading success stories of the creative world! I am going to build on this idea and will confidently say
that the ones who believe in students, will find them to be intensively creative. While if you choose to believe that the students are not creative
will find them to be unimaginative.&lt;br /&gt;
I choose to believe in the former and will continue to work with the young&amp;rsquo;uns to recharge my batteries :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom Designed Workshop</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/03/custom-designed-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 10:53:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/03/custom-designed-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image8.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image8.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image8&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do budding industrial designers, a professor in industrial design, couple of material scientists and an entrepreneur have in common? A thirst for novelty and the desire to help people. The venue was perfect with movable chairs, a whiteboard, projector, an audio system, just in case, we lost our ability to shout. Ranjan had arranged for flipcharts, markers and motivators. Motivators are little chocolate blocks, which go a long way in crafting excellent design from anyone. Shankar(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/shankarmv&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/shankarmv&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;), the lead facilitator, started off with a brief introduction on what innovation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bringing insightful ideas into a market”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tweet like mantra is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 stages of _!nnovation flow _-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape &amp;amp; Align&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move
Focus is the step where the entire attention is on &amp;ldquo;where the heck is the problem?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Escape &amp;amp; Align is about &amp;ldquo;What all can solve this problem?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Are my ideas science fiction or are they aligned to my organization/customers?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move is about &amp;ldquo;How do take it from here into the future?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bala(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/balaramadurai&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/nikimonikado&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/nikimonikado&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;) laid out the plan for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem selection &amp;amp; team formation Focus: 9 questions, Logo, Ideal Final Result, 5-Whys, function mapping Escape&amp;amp;Align: SCAMPER&amp;amp;IFR, Visual Business Model Move: Wasn’t covered as part of this workshop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sridhar(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/sridhardp&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/ThatvaTweet&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;) gave an overview of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thatva.com/&#34;&gt;Thatva&lt;/a&gt; which was a big part of the workshop as it gave a workspace for the teams to work out their ideas. The Thatva tool guided the teams to formalize their plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 ladies were appointed team captains and was asked to form their own teams of 4 members. There was intense chaos, but resulted in naturally formed cohesive teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task 1: Pick a socially relevant problem to solve and name your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task 2: Draw a good logo for your team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All logos are given below. Their logo pretty much depicts their problem statement as well. A fun way to focus, we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;logos&#34;&gt;Logos&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that made us facilitators worry about the sanity of the team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/scavenger.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/scavenger.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Scavenger&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/scavenger2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/scavenger2.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Scavenger- team in action&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whacky team, and a creative one!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that made us cry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/caresquare.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/caresquare.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Caresquare&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/caresquare2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/caresquare2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Caresquare - team in action&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Democracy at work, this team, everyone was listened to, well, almost everyone ;-)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that went thru more revisions than the colours on their logo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/helios.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/helios.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Helios&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you lack content, use colour :-)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that was corny&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/mealmonitors.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/mealmonitors.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;MealMonitors&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tagline says it all&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that had one guy do all the work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Leaf and newleafers leafing new leafs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-v0k128rvZLs/TtT7adY_-2I/AAAAAAAAAms/X-z1RKkKqZM/s720/DSC00678.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;H3O - the logo that required a long winded explanation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ideal-final-result-and-incubation&#34;&gt;Ideal Final Result and Incubation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the slogans, logo, initial discussions were over, ’twas analysis time. Top 3 benefits, 3 deficiencies, 3 dollar costs of the current situation was analyzed. 5-whys applied to find root cause of the problems, rather than stop at the first instance of trouble. The budding designers really liked the simplicity of the tool and the impact that the tool left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The smiling Prof. Chakrabarti&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incubation Time: The teams had to draw in pictures their problem with a funny restriction - No Words! SIPOC or supplier, inputs, process, output and customer was used as a template for the function mapping. This was given as overnight assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1 drew to a closure. We had promised a day of hardwork and so it was, big grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2 started with Sridhar guiding the teams to enter their output into Thatva and some basics on business plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was fun day - Started with silent brainstorming - Write down all ideas that pop in to your head to solve the problem as illustrated in the various tools of Focus. As much as 30 ideas emerged per team. Guided ideation - SCAMPER or substitute, combine, adapt, minimize/maximize, put to other use, eliminate, reverse was put to use. The teams found SCAMP quite good and added more ideas to their kitty. For Adapt, role play was used. Questions like &amp;ldquo;What would Superman do [if he were to solve your problem]?&amp;rdquo; not only sent out giggles around the room, but some unheard of ideas. Eliminate and Reverse were the toughest ones for the participants. Some really good ideas emerged for teams who persisted with their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does a team with a lot of ideas do? Giggle, snicker, doze and merge ideas into a concept. A concept chart was drawn out of all or most ideas during the session. This was presented amidst some power outages as seen in the pictures. Nothing stops enthusiastic students from presenting their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ended a great 2 half days for all of us. The students didn’t realize that they had taught the facilitators a great deal more than what was expected. A grand gala lunch followed in Nesara restaurant in IISc, Bangalore. We were richer by a few more facebook friends! Of course, a big thanks to Prof. Amaresh Chakrabarti and all his enthusiastic students who gave us the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other pictures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;622&amp;rdquo; caption=&amp;ldquo;The entire gang of participants, facilitators and the Professor&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/DSC00681.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The entire gang of participants, facilitators and the Professor&#34; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;576&amp;rdquo; caption=&amp;ldquo;Post workshop - Lunch at Nesara, IISc&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/DSC00683.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Post workshop - Lunch at Nesara, IISc&#34; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 steps to store and access anything anywhere</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/22/3-steps-to-store-and-access-anything-anywhere/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 14:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/22/3-steps-to-store-and-access-anything-anywhere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you gone to a high profile presentation only to discover that your latest version is in your home computer or office desktop?Have you ever wished that you didn&amp;rsquo;t have to carry your laptop anywhere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wanted to travel totally light, say carrying a pendrive and you lost the device?
Have you felt the need for your presentation software in a conference or in a client location?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your answer is yes to any one of the questions above, you will be able to relate to my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My selection criteria was simple: portable, light (physically) and I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be bothered with backing up or maintaining. And of course, investments should be, well, zero. I don&amp;rsquo;t prefer to carry music or videos with me, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Required:
USB pendrive of atleast 2GB capacity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One primary computer - desktop or laptop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 Signup on Dropbox for free 2GB space (Note- You can also add more space by doing certain steps as described in Dropbox)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;br /&gt;
If you want more free space (5GB), sugarsync is a good alternative.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/logo-ss.v2.png&#34; alt=&#34;SugarSync logo&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2 Download Portable apps platform with any applications from &lt;a href=&#34;http://portableapps.com&#34;&gt;portableapps.com&lt;/a&gt; on your pendrive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LibreOffice for Office apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chrome browser for browsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DSynchronize for synchronizing Pendrive and Dropbox/Sugarsync (with realtime sync)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vue.tufts.edu&#34;&gt;VUE&lt;/a&gt; for intuitive presentations (I copied the ProgramFilesVUE files and is now portable)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lyx for WYSIWYG LaTeX editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zotero.org/support/3.0&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; Standalone for storing research citations (works well with Chrome&amp;rsquo;s Zotero plug-in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skype (just in case, there is no skype on a machine I login)
3 Install dropbox app (or sugarsync desktop app) on your computer and designate a folder inside the Dropbox folder as Pendrive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image-1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/image-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are apps in portable apps to secure all files, folders and settings using a password. As luck would have it, I was invited to give a talk and I wanted to give a presentation using VUE and not powerpoint. I popped in my USB pendrive into the presentation machine, opened VUE from there and in less than a minute, I was ready to present without any hitches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I forgot to take my USB pendrive to a workshop, I was facilitating. No problem, I had sugarsync on my mobile device to retrieve all required files and apps. Oh yes, one could avoid the USB drive altogether with an app running on a mobile device, but that is a choice I leave it to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy wireless and careless life :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I will write about Skydrive, GMailDrive&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design Thinking Courses You May Like</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/1/01/01/design-thinking-courses-you-make-like/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/1/01/01/design-thinking-courses-you-make-like/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-design-thinking&#34;&gt;1. Design Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-creative-problem-solving&#34;&gt;2. Creative Problem Solving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-technology-forecasting&#34;&gt;3. Technology Forecasting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-intro-to-intrapreneurship&#34;&gt;4. Intro to Intrapreneurship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;5&#34;&gt;5.&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>