<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</title>
    <link>http://balaramadurai.net/categories/teaching/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) Dr. Bala Ramadurai; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://balaramadurai.net/categories/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Are students capable of coming out with blockbuster ideas?</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2012/05/12/are-students-capable-of-coming-out-with-blockbuster-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2012 07:14:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2012/05/12/are-students-capable-of-coming-out-with-blockbuster-ideas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/clapping.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/clapping.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Office Workers Clapping at Office Party&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raging debate in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://venture-lab.org&#34;&gt;team&lt;/a&gt; has been whether students (our team picked out undergraduate engineering students in
particular) are capable of generating blockbuster ideas for a thriving business/startup.&lt;br /&gt;
Before giving you both sides of the coin, I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you an anecdote about a large company trying to figure out what makes creative minds
creative. This large company was really curious to find out the real mechanism which made the creative minds work. So, they did surveys and profiling
to figure out (Education, cultural background, family details and so on) what was really happening in their minds. Zilch! They came out with no
concrete patterns or reasons for the creativity in their organization.&lt;br /&gt;
Second round was face to face interviews to see if they were missing out something obvious. After a few interviews, they hit upon the key insight that
they were looking for - creative guys thought that they were creative and the not-so-creative guys thought that they were not creative. Period!
Nothing else! (As a side note, this is what neuro linguistic programming (NLP) is all about :))&lt;br /&gt;
With this background in mind, I go back to the original debate of whether students will come out with ideas. Sure, the students who really believe
that they are creative will crack any problem given to them. The ones who think &amp;quot;Oh no, this is not my cup of tea to rub shoulders with the likes
of Edison&amp;quot;, will remain in the sideranks reading success stories of the creative world! I am going to build on this idea and will confidently say
that the ones who believe in students, will find them to be intensively creative. While if you choose to believe that the students are not creative
will find them to be unimaginative.&lt;br /&gt;
I choose to believe in the former and will continue to work with the young&amp;rsquo;uns to recharge my batteries :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom Designed Workshop</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/03/custom-designed-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 10:53:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/12/03/custom-designed-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image8.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image8.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image8&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do budding industrial designers, a professor in industrial design, couple of material scientists and an entrepreneur have in common? A thirst for novelty and the desire to help people. The venue was perfect with movable chairs, a whiteboard, projector, an audio system, just in case, we lost our ability to shout. Ranjan had arranged for flipcharts, markers and motivators. Motivators are little chocolate blocks, which go a long way in crafting excellent design from anyone. Shankar(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/shankarmv&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/shankarmv&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;), the lead facilitator, started off with a brief introduction on what innovation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bringing insightful ideas into a market”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tweet like mantra is all there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 stages of _!nnovation flow _-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escape &amp;amp; Align&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move
Focus is the step where the entire attention is on &amp;ldquo;where the heck is the problem?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Escape &amp;amp; Align is about &amp;ldquo;What all can solve this problem?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Are my ideas science fiction or are they aligned to my organization/customers?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move is about &amp;ldquo;How do take it from here into the future?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bala(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/balaramadurai&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/nikimonikado&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/nikimonikado&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;) laid out the plan for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem selection &amp;amp; team formation Focus: 9 questions, Logo, Ideal Final Result, 5-Whys, function mapping Escape&amp;amp;Align: SCAMPER&amp;amp;IFR, Visual Business Model Move: Wasn’t covered as part of this workshop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sridhar(&lt;a href=&#34;http://in.linkedin.com/in/sridhardp&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/ThatvaTweet&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;) gave an overview of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thatva.com/&#34;&gt;Thatva&lt;/a&gt; which was a big part of the workshop as it gave a workspace for the teams to work out their ideas. The Thatva tool guided the teams to formalize their plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 ladies were appointed team captains and was asked to form their own teams of 4 members. There was intense chaos, but resulted in naturally formed cohesive teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task 1: Pick a socially relevant problem to solve and name your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Task 2: Draw a good logo for your team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All logos are given below. Their logo pretty much depicts their problem statement as well. A fun way to focus, we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;logos&#34;&gt;Logos&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that made us facilitators worry about the sanity of the team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/scavenger.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/scavenger.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Scavenger&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/scavenger2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/scavenger2.png?w=300&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Scavenger- team in action&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Whacky team, and a creative one!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that made us cry&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/caresquare.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/caresquare.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Caresquare&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/caresquare2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/caresquare2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Caresquare - team in action&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Democracy at work, this team, everyone was listened to, well, almost everyone ;-)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that went thru more revisions than the colours on their logo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/helios.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/helios.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Helios&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you lack content, use colour :-)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that was corny&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/mealmonitors.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/mealmonitors.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;MealMonitors&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tagline says it all&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logo that had one guy do all the work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Leaf and newleafers leafing new leafs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-v0k128rvZLs/TtT7adY_-2I/AAAAAAAAAms/X-z1RKkKqZM/s720/DSC00678.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;H3O - the logo that required a long winded explanation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ideal-final-result-and-incubation&#34;&gt;Ideal Final Result and Incubation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the slogans, logo, initial discussions were over, ’twas analysis time. Top 3 benefits, 3 deficiencies, 3 dollar costs of the current situation was analyzed. 5-whys applied to find root cause of the problems, rather than stop at the first instance of trouble. The budding designers really liked the simplicity of the tool and the impact that the tool left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;img/image.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;img/image.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The smiling Prof. Chakrabarti&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incubation Time: The teams had to draw in pictures their problem with a funny restriction - No Words! SIPOC or supplier, inputs, process, output and customer was used as a template for the function mapping. This was given as overnight assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1 drew to a closure. We had promised a day of hardwork and so it was, big grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2 started with Sridhar guiding the teams to enter their output into Thatva and some basics on business plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was fun day - Started with silent brainstorming - Write down all ideas that pop in to your head to solve the problem as illustrated in the various tools of Focus. As much as 30 ideas emerged per team. Guided ideation - SCAMPER or substitute, combine, adapt, minimize/maximize, put to other use, eliminate, reverse was put to use. The teams found SCAMP quite good and added more ideas to their kitty. For Adapt, role play was used. Questions like &amp;ldquo;What would Superman do [if he were to solve your problem]?&amp;rdquo; not only sent out giggles around the room, but some unheard of ideas. Eliminate and Reverse were the toughest ones for the participants. Some really good ideas emerged for teams who persisted with their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does a team with a lot of ideas do? Giggle, snicker, doze and merge ideas into a concept. A concept chart was drawn out of all or most ideas during the session. This was presented amidst some power outages as seen in the pictures. Nothing stops enthusiastic students from presenting their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ended a great 2 half days for all of us. The students didn’t realize that they had taught the facilitators a great deal more than what was expected. A grand gala lunch followed in Nesara restaurant in IISc, Bangalore. We were richer by a few more facebook friends! Of course, a big thanks to Prof. Amaresh Chakrabarti and all his enthusiastic students who gave us the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other pictures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;622&amp;rdquo; caption=&amp;ldquo;The entire gang of participants, facilitators and the Professor&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;img/DSC00681.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;The entire gang of participants, facilitators and the Professor&#34; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; align=&amp;ldquo;alignnone&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;576&amp;rdquo; caption=&amp;ldquo;Post workshop - Lunch at Nesara, IISc&amp;rdquo;]&lt;img src=&#34;img/DSC00683.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Post workshop - Lunch at Nesara, IISc&#34; /&gt;[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 steps to store and access anything anywhere</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/22/3-steps-to-store-and-access-anything-anywhere/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 14:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2011/11/22/3-steps-to-store-and-access-anything-anywhere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you gone to a high profile presentation only to discover that your latest version is in your home computer or office desktop?Have you ever wished that you didn&amp;rsquo;t have to carry your laptop anywhere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wanted to travel totally light, say carrying a pendrive and you lost the device?
Have you felt the need for your presentation software in a conference or in a client location?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your answer is yes to any one of the questions above, you will be able to relate to my experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My selection criteria was simple: portable, light (physically) and I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be bothered with backing up or maintaining. And of course, investments should be, well, zero. I don&amp;rsquo;t prefer to carry music or videos with me, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Required:
USB pendrive of atleast 2GB capacity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One primary computer - desktop or laptop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 Signup on Dropbox for free 2GB space (Note- You can also add more space by doing certain steps as described in Dropbox)
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nikimonikado.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/image1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nikimonikado.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/image1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or&lt;br /&gt;
If you want more free space (5GB), sugarsync is a good alternative.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.sugarsync.com/images/logo-ss.v2.png&#34; alt=&#34;SugarSync logo&#34; /&gt;
2 Download Portable apps platform with any applications from &lt;a href=&#34;http://portableapps.com&#34;&gt;portableapps.com&lt;/a&gt; on your pendrive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LibreOffice for Office apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chrome browser for browsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DSynchronize for synchronizing Pendrive and Dropbox/Sugarsync (with realtime sync)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vue.tufts.edu&#34;&gt;VUE&lt;/a&gt; for intuitive presentations (I copied the ProgramFilesVUE files and is now portable)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lyx for WYSIWYG LaTeX editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zotero.org/support/3.0&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; Standalone for storing research citations (works well with Chrome&amp;rsquo;s Zotero plug-in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skype (just in case, there is no skype on a machine I login)
3 Install dropbox app (or sugarsync desktop app) on your computer and designate a folder inside the Dropbox folder as Pendrive.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://nikimonikado.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/image.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://nikimonikado.files.wordpress.com/2011/11/image.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are apps in portable apps to secure all files, folders and settings using a password. As luck would have it, I was invited to give a talk and I wanted to give a presentation using VUE and not powerpoint. I popped in my USB pendrive into the presentation machine, opened VUE from there and in less than a minute, I was ready to present without any hitches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I forgot to take my USB pendrive to a workshop, I was facilitating. No problem, I had sugarsync on my mobile device to retrieve all required files and apps. Oh yes, one could avoid the USB drive altogether with an app running on a mobile device, but that is a choice I leave it to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy wireless and careless life :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I will write about Skydrive, GMailDrive&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>