<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</title>
    <link>http://balaramadurai.net/tags/goals/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Dr. Bala Ramadurai | Professor &amp; Consultant in Innovation, Design Thinking, Intrapreneurship &amp; Technology Forecasting</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) Dr. Bala Ramadurai; all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="http://balaramadurai.net/tags/goals/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How did I plan my year to achieve my set goals</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2017/02/14/how-to-plan-to-achieve-your-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 07:34:23 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2017/02/14/how-to-plan-to-achieve-your-goals/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/1280px-Shanghai_2020_-_Urban_Planning_Exhibition_Center_-_03.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;Climb all you can&#34; class=&#34;img-responsive&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miniature view of Shanghai City - My metaphor for planning your goal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;flat-tyre-and-goals&#34;&gt;Flat tyre and Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My simple goal was to get back home from my vacation at Tarkarli on the Western Coast of India. I filled up my old faithful steed and meandered through the Western Ghats successfully. Although, I love the mountains, I am not very fond of driving on the serpentine, undivided roads. Another 20 kms for my Mooshika (my steed mentioned earlier has a name, that of a mouse) and me to hit the divided 6-lane motorway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25 minutes later, cruising down the Asian Highway 47 connecting Bangalore and Pune, I set my eyes on attaining my immediate goal of reaching home driving on the highway. I heard a dreadful noise and I cursed the other vehicles for NOT checking their tyre pressure. As it always happens, it was not the others who had a problem, but it was me. My steed had one problematic horse shoe (to continue the steed metaphor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25 minutes later, I wiped my dirty hands on a piece of paper from my pocket. Remember, I am a guy who writes goals on hotel bills? So, no surprise that I use pieces of paper to wipe my greasy hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as luck may have it, my goal sheet winked at me. Oh God, I had just wiped my dirty hands on my goal sheet!?! How am I supposed to plan for a year when I can&amp;rsquo;t even keep my goal sheet intact for a day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheet&amp;hellip;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-are-always-happening-to-me-time-to-take-action-and-break-down-those-goals&#34;&gt;Things are always happening to me, time to take action and break down those goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came back home, it took me a while to figure out under the greasy mess, what goals I had written out. Thankfully, I had a matrix of Strengths vs Audience and hence it was easy to figure out what I must have written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when I rewrote the goals in a computer file called Org mode, realization hit me like a cart full of mangoes. Some of the goals made me very uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So decided to make it easy for myself and decided to break it down. But how? What logic do I apply? I have had goals before and I have usually failed in achieving them. How should I stop myself from going down that path?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple enough, using the GTD methodology or Getting Things Done method (Watch intro video here - &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/Xduzwk04l2E&#34;&gt;https://youtu.be/Xduzwk04l2E&lt;/a&gt;). No, I don&amp;rsquo;t work for David Allen, the author of GTD, neither am I an affiliate. I am a practitioner of the GTD method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is this GTD method?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many things in the GTD method, I have picked up only one of the features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any venture or project that one takes up can have 2 things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the successful outcome? (the project is a done deal if this is achieved)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the next immediate action to get the project off the ground? (usually begins with an action verb - write, design, call, email, dance, whatever, who am i to judge)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tip from experience using this method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For seeing if you have written out the successful outcome part well or not is to answer the following question - is the project done or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer to that question can potentially be &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;, then you have done a good job. However, if your response lies between the two, in the dangerous territory of &amp;ldquo;maybe&amp;rdquo;, please consider rephrasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wrote down all my goals and wrote down these two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt; - if &amp;ldquo;writing&amp;rdquo; is one of your strengths and the audience is &amp;ldquo;children&amp;rdquo;. Then, &amp;ldquo;write a book for children&amp;rdquo; could be the goal you set for yourself for 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Successful outcome - &amp;ldquo;Children&amp;rsquo;s book published on Amazon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next action - &amp;ldquo;Write outline of the book&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You do this for all your goals. You can use a simple excel sheet to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-had-these-goals-in-front-of-me-but-there-s-just-too-many-of-them&#34;&gt;I had these goals in front of me, but there&amp;rsquo;s just too many of them&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I stared at the list of goals. That&amp;rsquo;s too many strengths and too many audiences vying for my attention and hence too many goals. X x Y = XY :) scary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;let-s-start-by-first-chunking-the-goals-into-categories&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start by first chunking the goals into categories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, let&amp;rsquo;s try and chunk these goals into a manageable list. It is said that we can only handle a max of 5 + or - 2 things at a time in your mind. Now, who said that and why did they say that I leave it to you. However, I realize that our human brain has a few limitations. Once, the list had a few goals under a few categories, I was satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are the few steps that one do to set a plan to attain those goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;assign-1-goal-per-quarter-per-category&#34;&gt;Assign 1 goal per quarter per category&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that you have 4 quarters in a year. You can split the quarters as 13 weeks in one quarter. I find this much easier because it is easier to set a reminder on Google Calendar later. But that is a matter of personal choice. You can use the frequency as once every 3 months or 13 weeks. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter. What matters is that you have one goal per quarter per category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next part of self-doubt crept into my mind - When do I achieve them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started allocating these goals and I want them all to be finished in the first quarter. So, if that were true, by the end of the first quarter, you should have one yourself 2 Grammies, 1 Nobel Peace Prize and a few awards along with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That won&amp;rsquo;t happen, so you will have to assign 1 goal per quarter per category. If you do, by some quirk of fate, do achieve a goal or two in the first quarter, then, leave yourself some stretch goals. Stretch goals are not fancy corporate words. This is a goal, that if you achieve will get your some self-brownie points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-common-place-where-my-goals-went-out-of-focus-was-in-tracking-progress&#34;&gt;The common place where my goals went out of focus was in tracking progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All right. Goals are set, quarters are assigned. Stretch goals are also there. Now what. Well, for one, things slipping through cracks when new stuff starts appearing throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one make sure you are on the right track. The answer is in that sentence - &amp;lsquo;track&amp;rsquo;ing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-will-have-a-weekly-quarterly-and-yearly-review-meeting-with-myself&#34;&gt;I will have a weekly, quarterly and yearly review meeting with myself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite way of tracking is through review meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 1-13 will have 13 weekly reviews and at the end of that period 1 quarterly review. No, no, not with your manager or your boss or your seven year old kid. With yourself. You will look at how things are going. You can do this tracking thing with pen and paper or get yourself a fancy, shiny app to do this. I leave it to you. But the important thing is to track or else your quarterly goals go haywire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 14-26, 27-39 and 40-52 or 53 will be the last quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My weekly reviews are on Friday afternoons - the dullest part of my week. At the end of the 13th week, for the 13th week, you will replace the weekly review with a quarterly review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-i-know-if-i-am-dedicating-enough-time-to-each-goal&#34;&gt;How do I know if I am dedicating enough time to each goal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your head is spinning at high velocities, I don&amp;rsquo;t blame you. This productivity thing is not easy to comprehend. It takes a lot of practice and patience. Once, you are past the initial phase, you are on to the intermediate level - time tracking. Here, you will know exactly how much time is it things take. You can use a kitchen timer like they do with the Pomodoro technique (aaawww, named after Tomatoes :))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use org-mode which comes in-built with a timer application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;usually-they-seem-fine-on-paper-but-how-do-i-not-go-off-track&#34;&gt;Usually, they seem fine on paper, but how do I not go off track?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review process will help you in case things go awry. My technique is to block the self weekly review on my calendar and I&amp;rsquo;ll never cancel this time (I may postpone or advance, but never cancel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;put-them-all-on-the-calendar-and-i-will-have-to-delete-them-if-i-don-t-do-it&#34;&gt;Put them all on the calendar and I will have to delete them if I don&amp;rsquo;t do it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly put the tasks on your calendar and never dismiss them. You can postpone them, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s how you achieve your goals in 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-no-wait-let-s-recap&#34;&gt;No, No, wait, let&amp;rsquo;s recap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine every goal and write the successful outcome and next action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chunk the goals and their next action into 5 + or - 2 categories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign one goal per quarter per category&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add in a stretch goal or two per category&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track progress using Weekly, Quarterly and Yearly Reviews, all Reviews scheduled on your favourite calendar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put all the next actions on your calendar and never delete them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you scrape through this for one year and having read this post till the very end, I&amp;rsquo;ll reward you with some used hotel receipts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do some vision things after a year of being at this goal thing. (How to set your life&amp;rsquo;s vision in 5 minutes - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vVsXO9brK7M&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vVsXO9brK7M&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I Set My Goals for 2017</title>
      <link>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2017/01/04/how-i-set-my-goals-for-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 10:40:12 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://balaramadurai.net/blog/2017/01/04/how-i-set-my-goals-for-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://balaramadurai.net/img/climb-1669121_1280.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Climb all you can&#34; class=&#34;img-responsive&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A speeding boat whirred in the Arabian Sea in full tilt. The horizon showed off four or five desolate islands right at the edge of my view from the balcony at a nice cozy resort in Tarkarli, Konkan Beach, Western India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to see what happened to the speeding boat. Did it stop or did it continue at the same speed? These questions become important when you are on a holiday doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about half an hour, the boat reappeared in my field of view. The person on the wonderful blue and white yacht did not drop an anchor or moor his boat to anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I waited the whole time to see what was going to happen to the boat. Will it hit the beach or one of those dreaded submerged rocks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boat drifted and bobbed with the gentle waves for the entire half an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, my mind drifted and thought about how I was exactly like that boat. I was adrift without any goals set for the year. I started to wallow in self-pity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-goals-set-and-a-rudderless-year-ahead-a-id-orgheadline2-a&#34;&gt;No goals set and a rudderless year ahead&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I drift like that boat or do I do something about this year that was coming up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2017&amp;#x2026;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow! In 7982 years from now, computer engineers will have the fright of their life and will fleece unwilling customers $10,000 per line of code to change four digit years to five digit years. I am sure, they will dub the problem as the Y10K problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oh! Wonderful times ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, back to my floating year ahead. What do I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;total-joblessness-at-tarkarli-beach-and-nothing-to-do-a-id-orgheadline3-a&#34;&gt;Total joblessness at Tarkarli beach and nothing to do&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline3&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to think about the previous year, 2016, where I had set a minimum number of goals for myself. I aced in some, but fell back in the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend had called me earlier and showed me the brighter side.&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Bala, you succeeded in some. That&amp;rsquo;s amazing! Most of us even forget about the goals we set at the start of the year.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I do know that he was being nice to me. Still, since I had nothing to do at the beach, all I could do was to think about random rubbish like setting goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;book-downloaded-heavy-lunch-all-chairs-taken-a-id-orgheadline4-a&#34;&gt;Book downloaded, heavy lunch, all chairs taken&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline4&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;rsquo;s when I decided to hit the comfy hanging chair in the balcony of our room at the resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A twenty kg problem presented itself.&lt;br /&gt;
My son had decided to occupy the exact same chair at the exact same time that I decided to plop. I was too lazy to give him the you-know-when-I-was-your-age-I-used-to-give-up-my-seat-to-my-elders talk. The other reason was that he&amp;rsquo;d WhatsApp my mom to find out if it were true. Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other chair had put madam to sleep in the wonderful, bright and sunny afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheesh! Where does a man go to sleep?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had had a heavy lunch, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to lie down to sleep. These blasted resort people had to make such yummy food. I looked around to see if I could find anything to sit on for snoozing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope, nothing, but the floor had a black device in the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my plastic book and sifted through the contents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiddy books, next page.&lt;br /&gt;
Kiddy books, next page.&lt;br /&gt;
Kitty books, next page.&lt;br /&gt;
Travel books, next page.&lt;br /&gt;
Italian and French books, next page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blast! This is MY virtual library too! Where are my books?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea - I clicked the &amp;ldquo;Last page&amp;rdquo; of the library button. Still no sign of the books that I had downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Archive&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There they were. All my books in the virtual attic of my virtual library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out e-book after e-book and my sight fell on the e-book - Martin Kaye&amp;rsquo;s book on &amp;ldquo;Goal Setting&amp;rdquo;. I had downloaded this from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.in/Setting-Workbook-Included-Step-Step-ebook/dp/B01BWO2JQU?ie=UTF8&#34;&gt;https://www.amazon.in/Setting-Workbook-Included-Step-Step-ebook/dp/B01BWO2JQU?ie=UTF8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yay!! A nerd dream come true. A goal setting book when I thought my life was about to become a rudderless boat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;book-reading-time-but-only-one-problem-a-id-orgheadline5-a&#34;&gt;Book reading time, but only one problem&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline5&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to read the book with gusto, since there were no people around me who were awake enough to ask me to order tea, or order me to take them down to the kiddy park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I fully understand that glorious Bagpiper ad meant - &amp;ldquo;You, me and Bagpiper&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I was. Plastic book in hand, me and an intensely nerdy topic in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowly sifted through page after page about positive psychology. Martin Kaye, the author, did a good job in detailing how the entire field of psychology had revolved around problem solving. He gave an amazing metaphor of climbing the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to love to climb and have a peak to climb. If you don&amp;rsquo;t love to climb and your happiness comes from reaching the peak. Then, your happiness may be short-lived. If you love to climb, but don&amp;rsquo;t have a peak in mind, then you may be going around in circles without really going anywhere (this scenario is akin to the rudderless boat mentioned at the start of this post and myriad other corporate meetings). Lastly, if you love to climb and you have a peak in front of you, you are all set, my friend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right-ho! I am with you, Martin! I was thoroughly convinced that this book was on the right track. I was all set to learn about goals and motivation, when I hit a stumbling block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book went something like this:&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ldquo;People who write down their goals are happier than people who type out their goals. You need the goal (the peak) and a list of strengths (the love of climbing). This goal thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for people who sit on the floor facing the balcony of a beach resort and passively read a book about goals and motivation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hey Martin, are you around here somewhere? in Konkan beach?&amp;rdquo; I looked around while thought to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, he didn&amp;rsquo;t exactly say those words, but the import was that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next logical step was to write stuff down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-paper-around-disastro-a-id-orgheadline6-a&#34;&gt;No paper around, disastro&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline6&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I had to lift myself up and look for writing materials. Whoever brings pens to beach resorts? Well, I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, notebooks, nope. None in the resort room either. They wanted you to go to the beach or be in that rudderless boat and not spend time writing your goals for the year inside the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was I going to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did that TRIZ problem solving guy tell me? Use resources around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I started to look around to see if I could find anything that I could use. Nope, nothing, but old hotel bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Useless, what should I do now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey! Wait a minute, yes, I will use the empty space on the back of those hotel bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goooooooooaaaaaaaaallllllllllll-x2026-a-id-orgheadline7-a&#34;&gt;Goooooooooaaaaaaaaallllllllllll&amp;#x2026;..&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline7&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I start and what do I do after that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, this is what I did. The following method is a combination of what the book said and some of my own thoughts because of what was mentioned in the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengths&lt;/strong&gt; - Write your strengths down.example - you may be good at public speaking or organizing or coding or gardening. Whatever&amp;#x2026;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audiences&lt;/strong&gt; - Write the audiences you work with or you want to work with
example - your boss, your spouse, your team, your clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strengths vs. Audiences&lt;/strong&gt; - Make a table of strengths vs audiences
&lt;table border=&#34;3&#34; cellspacing=&#34;2&#34; cellpadding=&#34;12&#34; rules=&#34;all&#34;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Strength/Audience&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Client 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Client 2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Team&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Boss&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Spouse&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Me&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Public Speaking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Organizing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Coding&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Gardening&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think&lt;/strong&gt; - Make a pair of strength and audience and think of how you can help the audience with your strength.&lt;br /&gt;
Spend some time thinking about this combo. Example - How can my public speaking strength be useful for my team? How can that strength benefit them?
&lt;table border=&#34;3&#34; cellspacing=&#34;2&#34; cellpadding=&#34;12&#34; rules=&#34;all&#34;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Strength/Audience&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Client 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Client 2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Team&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Boss&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Spouse&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Me&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Public Speaking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Organizing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Coding&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Gardening&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
5. &lt;strong&gt;Finish thinking&lt;/strong&gt; - about all these combinations
&lt;table border=&#34;3&#34; cellspacing=&#34;2&#34; cellpadding=&#34;12&#34; rules=&#34;all&#34;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;col  class=&#34;org-left&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Strength/Audience&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Client 1&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Client 2&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Team&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Boss&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;My Spouse&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope=&#34;col&#34; class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Me&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Public Speaking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(2)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(3)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(5)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(4)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Organizing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(7)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(8)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Coding&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(6)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(6)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(6)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(9)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(13)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;Gardening&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;(11)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;org-left&#34;&gt;&amp;#xa0;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1), (2) and (3) Hold public speaking courses for Client 1, Client 2 and My Team once a quarter, so that they can learn from my strength of public speaking.&lt;br /&gt;
(5) Use my public speaking strengths to help my spouse be assertive at her work place.&lt;br /&gt;
(4) I will join Toast Master&amp;rsquo;s club to learn from others in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and so on and so forth. Finish outlining all the goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-goals-set-for-2017-a-id-orgheadline8-a&#34;&gt;All goals set for 2017&lt;a id=&#34;orgheadline8&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the 5 steps above to set goals for myself for 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that time, my son left his seat at the hanging chair and headed downstairs to play in the park. Madam had left the balcony to order tea for us. How nice of her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dude with the yacht had a nice solid anchor down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you waiting for? Go ahead and set your goals for 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time, I will tell you about how I plan to put them into action.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>